## Ms. Sagun Basnet

New Baneshor, Ward No. 34, Kathmandu, Nepal tel: +(977) 98511 19019 | email: sagunbasnet@gmail.com

#### **SUMMARY STATEMENT**

As a student of inter-disciplinary discourses, my experiences capture the theme well. My work experiences enclose academics, media and development sector and the bloodline for all this has been an aim of behaviour change communication. This has given me confidence to work alongside a range of people from many walks of life. With every learning thus, I gather broad range of skills and knowledge to function in a multicultural team with multi-perception. I am fluent in Nepali, English and Hindi, can understand Bhojpuri and Maithili and can to a certain extent, understand Newari.

#### **HONOURS**

- Fulbright Scholarship Award 2008-2010.
- Dean's list in MPhil.
- Scholarships for all the consecutive years of Master's and Bachelor's Degrees.

#### **EDUCATION**

# 2010 Master of Arts (MA) in Social and Cultural Analysis from New York University, New York, USA. [Graduated with Honors]

Two years of extensive interdisciplinary course, that incorporated conflict and violence, race and gender. social structures, history, economy and human rights.

- A three credit course on Conflict Transformation Across Cultures (CONTACT) organized by SIT Graduate Institute/World Learning, Vermont, USA (1-19 June, 2009)
- 2008 Master of Philosophy (M Phil) from Institute of Advanced Communications Education and Research (IACER), Pokhara University, Nepal. [Dean's List]

One and a half years of extensive course on interdisciplinarity that incorporates Gender, Social Changes, Conflict Studies, and Creative writing.

2003 Master of Arts (MA) in English from Patan Multiple Campus, Tribhuwan University, Nepal.

Two years of interdisciplinary courses that incorporated theories on gender, postcolonialism, decolonization, non western studies, modernity/postmodernity, philosophy, and Creative Writing.

### **ACADEMIC/ TEACHING EXPERIENCES**

## Institute of Advance Communication, Education and Research (IACER), Faculty

Kathmandu, Nepal Jan 2011 – date

- Designed and delivered courses on 'Foundation course on conflict and peace studies' and 'Multi-disciplinary approaches to conflict transformation' for Masters level students.

# Patan Multiple College, Tribhuwan University, Assistant Lecturer (part-time)

Kathmandu, Nepal Dec 2004 – Jun 2007

- Focus on race, gender and identity issues on the location of modern English and American societies with an analysis of 'Modern English' and 'American Poetry' to Masters level students.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCES

# Equal Access Nepal (EAN) – <a href="https://www.equalacceess.org.np">www.equalacceess.org.np</a> Coordinator of Programs and Business Development

Kathmandu, Nepal Aug 2010 – till date

- Proiect Management:
  - Lead the management of programs with a focus on Gender Mainstreaming, VAW, Conflict Transformation and Peacebuilding and Health.
- Leading Conflict and Peace Related Projects:
  - "Communities and Media United for Peace": An initiative that aims to document the attacks and threats on journalists via radio and television documentaries. An aim that would foster secured environment for journalists working in conflict affected environments.
  - Local Radio Comes to Kathmandu": Increasing Capacity of Radio Journalists. An intensive project that focused on orienting the media people on their positive role on constitution writing and peace process.

- ♣ "Peace Media Network (PMN)", a loose network of journalists from Kathmandu, Makwanpur and Sunsari formed by EAN and UNWOMEN with an aim to reduce violence against women and increase their participation in the peace process of Nepal.
- Leading Gender Based Violence (GBV) and Violence against Women (VAW) related projects:
  - Sahamati" Mobilizing Media for raising awareness on GBV. The initiative is funded by UNWOMEN and aims to fight GBV by mobilizing the power of media (radio here) for transformation.
  - "Jeevan Jyoti" Using radio to raise awareness and fight the gendered role in Family Planning, Neo-natal and Child Health.
  - # "Sangsangai": a radio program which aimed to reduce violence against women attaching itself to the We Can End Violence against women campaign of OXFAM.
  - "Mamata", funded by the World Bank, focused on gender perspective of nutrition.
- Documentation and Reporting:
  - Working and supervising the program managers for drafting and finalizing the quarterly and annual progress reports making sure the reports go in timely manner and in good quality regarding messages and language. In order to implement the programs, I have been consistently ensuring the program content, organizing regular trainings, overseeing project budgets and working closely with the Monitoring and Evaluation team to keep track of the effectiveness of the project activities.
- Project Design and Business Development:
  - Co-leading the business development team as Biz Dev Coordinator and have been able to secure funding for the organization. Worked closely with business development team to address new project opportunities, especially by providing inputs for technical design of the new projects/proposals, writing them, collecting, and collating necessary information and documents to support the proposal development.
  - ♣ A vital part of this includes representing Equal Access Nepal at local meetings with donors and stakeholders. A crucial milestone for this was representing EAN in Action Asia's peacebuilders' forum in Cambodia in October 2010. A presentation on "transforming my woundedness for peace" was quite well received by the participants and the organizers for its content on "gender and peacebuilding". http://www.actionasia.org/publications/

# Friends for Peace – <a href="https://www.friendsforpeace.org.np">www.friendsforpeace.org.np</a> Gender and Peacebuilding Team Leader/ Communications Officer

Kathmandu, Nepal Mar 2007 – Jul 2008

- Lead research on Gender and Peacebuilding and coordinate with researchers and researches in the area.
- ♣Developed and conducted sessions on Gender and Peacebuilding in various trainings.
- Coordinated external communications with other NGOs, donors, media and wider public with regard to research and information.
- **♣**Developed and implemented communication strategy in collaboration with other staff including dissemination of research and information in and outside the valley.
- **♣**Contributed to strategic planning of the organization and generated ideas around communication and dissemination.
- ♣Monitored news and events and updated website.
- Edited and packaged research and briefing papers (newsletter, annual report, brochures) bilingually.
- **♣**Organized events such as seminars, public meetings, workshops and consultations.

### Dig Darshan Media Researcher/ Scrip Writer/ Narrator (part-time)

Kathmandu, Nepal Mar 2003 –Mar 2007

- Researched, wrote and narrated and co- edited a project based documentary, 'Teacher's role in Education for All' for Action Aid Nepal. The documentary raised questions on the envisaged dream of 'Education for All' and brought the drop-out rates of girl child and exclusion of ethnic minorities and conflict victims in secondary education system.
- Researched, wrote and narrated and co-edited a project based documentary, 'Vocational education an alternative' for Training for Employment Project. The research focused on, providing vocational education to the marginalized, minorities, children and girls who have dropped secondary education.
- Researched, wrote, narrated, and co-edited a project-based documentary, 'Tireless hands' for Rural Enterprise Development Program. The research focused on, small and micro enterprises for empowerment through inclusion of women, children and marginalized community of Ilam, Panchthar, Taplejung, Humla and Jumla.

### Nepal Television Editor/ News Presenter

Kathmandu, Nepal Mar 2003 – Mar 2007

- ♣Monitor and report the developments in Nepal's peace process (including the role of United Nations Mission in Nepal (UNMIN).
- ♣Report, Research, Interview, translate (Nepali- English-Nepali), edit and proofread news; Work as a news producer/anchor.

### Researcher/Program Anchor

*Jan 2006 – May 2006* 

- **♣**Carry out field research, write script and anchor 18-episode television program 'Antar Drishti' produced by Dig Darshan Media and broadcast on Nepal Television.
- **♣**Create the program as a forum for exchange of pains and possible solutions of problems of women, Dalits, marginalized, children, child labor, People living with HIV/AIDS and conflict and HIV/AIDS orphans.
- ♣Through discussions and interviews, mainstream the discourses on basic and vocational education for the above mentioned people.
- ♣Appraise the audience about the rules and regulations of the education sector and hold discussions with educationists and experts.

## Higher Secondary Education Board (HSEB) Curriculum and Training Officer

Bhaktapur, Nepal Feb 2004 – Jul 2006

- \*Research the status of the marginalized, women, children and excluded communities and prepare plans for curriculum packages to address the research and produce it in board meetings.
- Research for bringing about uniformity between educational structures of Nepal and other countries especially SAARC nations; Facilitate and organize trainings for higher secondary teachers; Editorial assistance for documentations, high school membership directory format and HSEB journal 'Sampreshan'.
- **♣** Supervise and monitor the Higher Secondary Schools in course of the implementation of curricula developed by the board.
- ♣ Establish liaison with the international educational institutions in connection with the verification of certificates and development of curricula.

# Town Development Fund (TDF) Senior Office Assistant

Bhaktapur, Nepal Aug 1999 – Feb 2004

- **Coordinated and organized regular meetings and workshops with various municipalities, departments and line agencies of Nepal Government, National and International Organizations and local bodies.**
- ♣Co-researched and collected data of the number of pro-poor in the project areas viz: Banepa, Bhadrapur, Damak, Hetauda and Kapilvastu Municipalities.
- ♣Assisted the municipalities in selecting the pro poor vicinity and writing proposals.
- ♣Prepare minute of the board decisions and circulate.
- Work out the responsibilities of office administration viz: preparing project reports, booklets and information materials for the promotion of town development, preparing and translating the official reports. (Nepali-English-Nepali) maintaining staffs' personnel records, filings, staff leaves, content of web page and develop promotional materials.
- ♣ Worded as an Associate to the Secretary (In Deputation from TDF) in the Ministry of Physical Planning and Works (September 2000 July 2002).

#### MAJOR RESEARCH, ARTICLES AND PUBLICATIONS

### **Research on Gender Based Discriminations**

- *Microcredit: the Creative Discourse of Empowerment Economy :* focusing on how, besides being very benign, microcredit and neoliberal policies are exacerbating gender based unfair advantages in Bangladesh and Nepal.
- Indentured Servitude: At What Price?: analysis of locating Universal Declaration of Human Rights in particular cultures and transgressions with particular focus on the Kamlari System of Nepal.
- Marketing Nepal: an analysis of the Kumari system of Nepal sharing intersections with Tourism and commoditization of women.
- The Chhaupadi System of Nepal and International Women's Day: An analysis of the human rights of the women who are excluded every month from homes because they bleed.
- Reintegration Initiatives for Trafficked Women: A research focused on why the reintegration approaches of trafficked women face major problems in Nepal.
- The inner nuances of sex trade in cabin restaurants and massage centre in Thamel, Kathmandu and presented the findings in a seminar on conflict transformation.
- Women and Politics: Is voting enough?: focused on the qualitative participation of women i.e. whether they decide on whom to vote by themselves or are guided by family. This research based on check list tried to go beyond the hitherto literatures that saw good participation in numbers and not reason.
- A research entitled *Construction Of Femininity In A Racial Society As A Form Of Resistance* done for the completion of MA Degree.

 Songs of Meerabai: Devotion, Body and Sexuality done for the completion of MPhil Degree focusing on the right of women over her body and sexuality. (Grades obtained A)

### **Research on Social and Cultural Discriminatory Practices**

 Researched the status and needs of child laborers born as victims and orphans of conflict, focusing on the random selection at Kalimati area of Kathmandu valley. The voices of these children were broadcast through "Antardrishti" program (mentioned above)

### **Academic Papers on Gender Based Discriminations**

- Article on "Chhaupadi and International Women's day"
- Article on "Women and Politics: Is voting enough?"
- Article on "Who needs awareness the HIV infected women or the policy makers?"
- Article on "All men are created equal?"
- Article on "Post Ceasefire Responsibilities".
- Academic paper on Commodification of female bodies.
- Academic paper on female body and sexuality as a social construct.

#### SHORT-TERM CONSULTANCIES

- **Program Evaluation Consultant** for *Search for Common Ground* Nepal <a href="www.sfcg.org">www.sfcg.org</a> Jun Aug 2010 Carried out programmatic evaluation of Search for Common Ground (SFCG) Nepal focusing on the overall impact of SFCG's programs on peace at large. The evaluation is based on the premise that the findings of the evaluation will be a learning opportunity for the organizations, its partners and other organizations working in the area of peacebuilding.
- Documentation and Communication Consultant for Action Aid Asia Initiative Asian People's Alliance for Combating HIV and AIDS (APACHA) <a href="www.apachenet.org">www.apachenet.org</a>. Supported the Communication and Network strategy of Asian Pacific People's Alliance to combat HIV and AIDS (APACHA) an Action Aid Asia initiative. I also edited the content and concept of APACHA website which has developed in the concept of web based knowledge initiative. APACHA is working in ten different countries across Asia and its regional secretariat is in Kathmandu.
- Media Consultant for Swati, a NGO working for women empowerment and good governance.
   Edited, translated and proof read the Swati journal 'Astitwa' and also worked as a rapporteur and report writer in its programs. Produced audio messages on anti-corruption.
- Researcher for Nepal National Commission for UNESCO
   Conducted a research on Role of women in eradicating HIV/AIDS, which focused on the role of HIV infected and affected women in eradicating the stigma and discrimination.
  - Conducted a research on *Socio-economic condition of Musahar*, a marginalized community in the Mid Eastern plains of Nepal focusing on Siraha, Sunsari and Udaypur districts of Nepal.

#### **TRAINING**

- Conflict Transformation Across Cultures (CONTACT) organized by SIT Graduate Institute/World Learning, Vermont, USA (1-19 June, 2009)
- Leadership Development Skills organized by Skillshare International (11-14 March 2008).
- Craft of Television Journalism and News Gathering organized by Associated Press Television News (APTN) (October 2006)
- Editorial and Anchoring Skills organized by Nepal Television. (March May 2003)
- Learning about Tuberculosis and DOTS, HIV&AIDS and Differently ableness in terms mental health organized by District Health Office, Lalitpur (January 1996)

### **PASSION**

- Writing http://sagunbasnet.wordpress.com and
- Being a proud mom, experiencing 13th year of motherhood.

#### **REFERENCES**

Provided upon request.